<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A declaration of the great and weighty affayres and matters of consequence concerning this kingdome. Also the severall orders made by the House of Parliament, March 22. 1641. With some remarkeable occurrences from Holland, and the kingdome of Ireland. Printed by order of the House of Parliament, March 22. 1641. Hen. Elsinge, Cler. Parl. Dom. Com.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 16 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A82162</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D684</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E140_28</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860697</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860697</idno>
            <idno type="VID">156549</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A82162)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 156549)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 25:E140[28])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A declaration of the great and weighty affayres and matters of consequence concerning this kingdome. Also the severall orders made by the House of Parliament, March 22. 1641. With some remarkeable occurrences from Holland, and the kingdome of Ireland. Printed by order of the House of Parliament, March 22. 1641. Hen. Elsinge, Cler. Parl. Dom. Com.</title>
                  <author>Hunt, Raphael, 17th cent. Very joyfull news from Ireland.</author>
                  <author>Newton, William, One of the gentleman ushers unto the Lady Elizabeth. Coppie of a letter written by Master William Newton to his brother Francis Newton.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Thomas,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641 [i.e. 1642]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴.</note>
                  <note>Thomason copy bound with items from 1642.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:156549:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:156549:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DECLARATION of the Great and weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Affayres and Matters of Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence concerning this Kingdome.</p>
            <p>Alſo the ſeverall Orders made by the Houſe of Parliament, <hi>March</hi> 22, 1641.</p>
            <p>With ſome Remarkeable Occurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces from <hi>Holland,</hi> and the Kingdome of <hi>IRELAND.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="license">
                           <p>Printed by Order of the Houſe of Parliament, <date>
                                 <hi>March</hi> 22. 1641.</date>
                           </p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>Hen. Elſinge, Cler. Parl. Dom. Com.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Thomas.</hi> 1641.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="declaration">
            <pb facs="tcp:156549:2"/>
            <head>Expreſſe Commands from both the Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Houſes of Parliament.</head>
            <p>WHereas the Abuſes and Vſurpations of the Papiſts in their Religion, hath given cauſe to the poore Subjects of this his Majeſties Kingdome, to preſent divers Peitions unto this Honourable Aſſembly; therein deſiring reliefe and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance from their eminent grievances, appearing by reaſon of their too much power over them, and over-much duty to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Pope; by which occaſion they deny that authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and ſupremacy belonging to his Majeſty over the Church, contributing the ſame unto his Holineſſe, who is their ſupream head; as alſo, being men of abilities for the moſt part, thay uſe extream rigour towards choſe Tenants, who are Proteſtants, not onely in the way of exaction of their due before the time it ſhould grow payable, but alſo by raiſing their Rents year<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by renewing of Fines, and laying other exactions upon them; we therefore having been moved often in this behalfe, taking it into our conſideration have Ordered concerning the ſame, as followeth.</p>
            <p n="1">1 That all Papiſts and Recuſants within this his Majeſties Kingdome of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales,</hi> of what condition, ſtate, or ability ſoever, denying to take the <hi>Oath of Supremacy,</hi> admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred unto them by a Juſtice of the Peace, be forthwith com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to priſon in his Majeſties Goaie next adjoyning, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they give ſecurity for their appearance at the next Seſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, their ſurety being bound in the value of 1000. l. to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the party, or parties ſo denying the ſame.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Concerning thoſe Knights and Gentlemen within this Kingdome, who are Recuſants, and whoſe Tenants are Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſtants: It is Ordered, that the Rent of their Lands, Leaſes Houſe, or houſe-roome be valued and payed for according to
<pb facs="tcp:156549:2"/>the proportion that other Neighbours adjoyning, ſhall pay to their Proteſtant Landlords, there being deducted out of the ſaid ſum upon every pound to be diſtributed to the poore, the ſumme of twelve pence.</p>
            <p n="3">3 That as for thoſe perſons Papiſts, who ſhall be proved to have any mutuall concurrence with the Rebels in <hi>Ireland</hi> in theſe wayes, either for ſupplyes of Victuall, contribution of money, loan, or ſuch like, their goods be confiſcate to the King, and thoſe that ſhall deſire the ſame, ſhall have a reward from the Parliament.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="Parliamentary_order">
            <head>The Order concerning fortifying His Majeſties Forts and Caſtles.</head>
            <p>THere being likewiſe divers Petitions delivered to this Honourable Aſſembly, to free them from thoſe feares of Innovations, by reaſon of his Majeſties Forts in the County of <hi>South-hampton,</hi> and the Iſle of <hi>Wight,</hi> not being Fortified as they ought to have beene in ſome of them; there being not above two, others three pieces of Ord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, fit for ſervice: alſo others not having Powder and Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munition to reſſiſt Innovations; For the amendment of which, and Removall of the Country Grievances, it was Ordered:</p>
            <p n="1">1 That the Cattles of <hi>Yarmouth,</hi> the <hi>Cows Hurſt</hi> Caſtle, <hi>Southſide</hi> Caſtle, <hi>Dunſe</hi> Caſtle <hi>Morby</hi> Port, <hi>Newſton</hi> Port in the Iſle of <hi>Wight,</hi> the Caſtles of <hi>Weymouth, Purbeck; Nelſon. Holibey, Darkingdon, Mockliffe, Painſwick, Harrowbey, Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, Walloway, Aggerton,</hi> and <hi>Veſtoll</hi> in the County of <hi>Dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſot.</hi> The Caſtles of <hi>Tanton Dean, Appleby, Brownſoad, Bridg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water, Pimbley,</hi> and <hi>Norton</hi> in the County of <hi>Somerſet,</hi> with all other his Majeſties Caſtles within the aforeſaid Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſhould be every one provided with 100. of the beſt and moſt ableſt men, neare and neighbouringly adjoyning to the ſaid Caſtles, choſen out of the Train-Bands of the ſaid Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; and ſuch as ſhall not faile in performance of their duty therein.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That every one of the ſaid Caſtles be fortifled with ten pieces of Ordnance at the leaſt, well mounted, and ſit for ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb facs="tcp:156549:3"/> 3 That the Captain of the Caſtle be a man noted for a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious perſon, and not given to the <hi>Catholique Roman Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> but to be carefull of performing that duty impoſed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his charge. But if in caſe they ſhall prove otherwiſe, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on juſt complaint and proofe thereof be diſcharged; accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Order now Enacted.</p>
            <p n="4">4 That to every of the aforeſaid Caſtles, there be allowed as many Gunnes as Ordnance; beſides, every Gunner to have his Matiſe or man to attend him.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="Parliamentary_order">
            <head>An Order made by the Houſe of Parliament, concerning the ſuppreſſing of thoſe men, that are ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together in a warlike manner in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of <hi>Durham.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>WHereas by Letters written by the Sheriffe, and divers Iuſtices of peace of the County of <hi>Durham,</hi> to an Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable Member of this Houſe, and this day read in this houſe, It doth appeare that great Multitudes of People have of late aſſembled themſelves at ſeverall times, in ſeverall places of that County, to the number of three or foure Hundred in one Company in Warlike manner, vpon a pretence of pulling downe ſome incloſurs, which they have already done in a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry outragious manner in ſome parts of the County, and threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to doe the like in other parts, And for that, this Houſe conceiveth that ſuch tumultuous and diſorderly meetings are altogether in themſelves vnlawfull, and may in theſe times prove of very dangerous conſequence. It is therefore this day, Ordered by the Houſe of Commons, that the Juſtices of peace of the ſaid County ſhall make diligent inquitie after the names of ſuch Perſons, as were the chiefe Leaders in the ſaid tumultuous aſſemblies, or any of them and certifie their names forthwith to this Houſe, that ſuch ſpeedy and exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plarie courſes may be held againſt them as to Law and Juſtice appertaines. And for the f<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e it is farther Ordered, that if any tumultuous aſſemblies or routs of people, vpon any
<pb facs="tcp:156549:3"/>pretence whatſoever ſhall at any time hereafter be made in any part of the ſaid County, that the ſaid Iuſtices of peace &amp; Sheriffe ſhall by all wayes and meanes poſſible endeavour to ſuppreſſe the ſame, and that if need be, the Sheriffe ſhall goe with the power of the County to arreſt ſuch offenders and Riotours and ſhall Arreſt them, and the ſaid Juſtices and Sheriffe ſhall record that which they ſhall ſo find done in their preſence againſt the Law, and if it happen that ſuch treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſers and offenders ſhall be ſcattered and departed before the comming of the ſaid Juſtices and Sheriffe, that the ſaid Juſtices or any three or two of them ſhall diligently enquire after ſuch aſſembly and Rout of people ſo made, and ſhall doe therein, what by the Statute and Lawes of this Realme they are enabled to doe, and they are hereby further required to certifie the names of offenders and their further proceedings in the premiſſes to this Houſe, That in caſe ſuch offenders ſhall by their Multitudes as otherwiſe evade ſuch puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as the Juſtices of the Peace can inflict upon them.</p>
            <p>Then this Houſe may take the ſame into further conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and take ſuch courſes for Puniſhing the offenders as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Juſtice ſhall be thought meete.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſſe this Houſe doth further declare, that if any Perſon or Perſons whatſoever be injured by any incloſure of late made in this County without juſt Warrant of Law or conſent of parties vpon their addreſſe to this Houſe by Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titon otherwiſe of their juſt complaint. This Houſe will bee carefull to take ſpeedy courſe for their reliefe as ſhall bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to Juſtice. And will alſo take into conſideration in due time the Petition now remaining before them: againſt the Biſhop of <hi>Durham</hi> and others, for their incloſuers. And the Sheriffe of the Countie is likewiſe hereby required to publiſh this Order that it may be taken notice of throughout the Countie.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="copy_of_letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:156549:4"/>
            <head>The Coppie of a Letter, written by Maſter <hi>William Nowton,</hi> one of the Gentleman Vſhets unto the Lady <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> unto his Brother <hi>Francis Newton,</hi> Eſq and one of the Foure Squires of the Body to his Majeſtie.</head>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From the Hage,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>March the</hi> 18. <hi>New ſtile,</hi> 1641.</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Brother,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WEE are here at the <hi>Hage,</hi> but in little bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter caſe, as touching feares and Iealouſies, then you are in <hi>England:</hi> true, the matter of the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> is ſeemingly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, J wiſh I could ſay ended, fire raked up, may poſſibly appeare, yea and flame: The States will not truſt him with monies. and paying of the Armie, as formerly, but will ſet up and create a new Officer for that purpoſe, this ſometimes diſcontents his Highneſſe, the Governor of <hi>Bergin up Zone,</hi> that towne of ſo great ſtrength, being once a neere ſervant to his Highneſſe, and brought up a long time under him, in very neere ſervices, and preferred unto that great place of truſt by the Princes mediation, him would the States now very faine remove; but the talke goes here that he will not hearken to it, having that great garriſon firme on his ſide; as it is feared upon too juſt grounds; the Prince hath all the Armie, ſo that wee are not yet here quite cleer of all furmizes of after claps the Burgers in the Townes, plainely give out, that they feare the Prince has been aforehand with them, and one of the Burgemaſters of <hi>Fluſhing,</hi> openly in my Mr. the Princes-pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence Chamber, told my Lord <hi>Goring,</hi> in my hearing, that they had juſt cauſe to feare, that the Princes Sons Marriage with the eldeſt daughter of the King of great Brittaine, had ſet the Prince on ſuch a high ſtraine, that ſhortly he doubted either their ruine or his owne, pray God things ſtand as they were, for unwonted aſpiring thoughts, produce many times enterprizes more pleaſing then ſucceſſfull, if diſtempers ſhould againe breake out heere: I thinke we muſt be forted to come and viſite you in England, truth is, the States General have never the better opinion of the Prince ſince this match, ſome
<pb facs="tcp:156549:4"/>thinke the worſe, nay their uſuall reſpects are ſomething col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der toward my Lady, and Maſter, who J dare ſay upon oath, is heartily grieved for this difference, and diſcorreſpondencie between the Prince and them, and hath no intereſt or part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerſhip but ſorrow in in it, and who muſt reape diſconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence by it, and may account this to the reſt of her croſſes the Queenes entertainment at the <hi>Hage,</hi> is in my very ſoule more royall then heartie the Dutch liberalitie is almoſt at an end and the Queenes entertainment begins to ſlacken with them, only his Highneſſe houlds on his wonted nobleneſſe in chearing her, they ſet her Majeſtie a day, that they would be rid of her, if ſo it pleaſe or ſtand with her occaſions, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation is made againſt your Parliament delinquents, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding them ſtrictly to repayre hither during her Majeſties abode here upon paine of impriſonment, and ſending backe into England with ſtrict guard, hath been here publiſhed in all Townes and Dominions of the States, yet two have brave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly adventured to kiſſe her hand, who came hither wonderful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly well diſguiſed and walked not openly in Court, lay in the Prince of Oranges ownelodging, and after two dayes tooke leave to goe to Bruſiels, God knowes the Queene is very narrowly warched here, as a perſonage of her quality may be, and I durſt pawne my life the Parliament hath ſome agents here meerely to attend that buſines, and three of them are in my Conſcience <hi>L. O. S. S. J. H.</hi> Her Majeſtie would have gone to Cullen, to have attended upon her Mother, then to Bruſſels, but was denied, the Prince of Orange ſeemed very forward to accompliſh her deſire in both, as farre as in his power, but he was not ſo forward, but ſhe found the Dutch as froward, who abſolutely denyed in plaine termes, ſtudying all the wayes they can to gratifie and comply with the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, not caring who they diſpleaſe, ſo they ſatisfie them, I verely thinke the Queen as the matter ſtands will not trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble them long here, and that yee ſhall have her in England yet a good while before Eaſter.</p>
            <p>Thus hoping your welfare, and all our contents from his Highneſſe Court at the <hi>Hage</hi> this preſent Friday, <hi>March</hi> the 18., J remaine your ever true and loving Brother and Servant,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Wil. Newton.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:156549:5"/>
            <opener>
               <date>
                  <hi>March</hi> 22.</date>
            </opener>
            <head>Very Joyfull Newes from <hi>Jreland.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Maſter <hi>John Ha<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>kredge:</hi>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Have written by the two laſt Poſts, and now J have got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten a lame hand: but having good Newes, it ſhall trot to impart it unto you. The laſt Saturday the Lord <hi>Moore</hi> and Sir <hi>Henry Titchbourne</hi> fallyed out of the Towne, and fell upon the enemies, and drove them out of their Trenches, and raiſ'd their ſiege, ſlew about 350, of their men, and tooke many of their chiefe Officers, and have relieved themſelves bravely, and tooke 150, of their Muskers, and a field full of Pikes, we having loſt as ſome affirme, no men. Here are three of our Captaines come by Land, ſo that this Newes is true. Vpon Munday our Forces went out, 4000. Foot and 500. Horſe, they are already within 5. myles of <hi>Tredagh:</hi> by the way; Lievtenant Colonell <hi>Read</hi> came in to our men, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted; if he had not done it, he could not have fled: he is ſent hither, and lodg'd in the Caſtle. I doe believe we ſhall now get good ſtore of Corne out of the Country, which will keepe the price from riſing. Our men are not expected home this weeke, pray God keepe them ſafe. Sir <hi>Philimy Oneale</hi> was in the Battell, but was faine to ſlye; and that was not like to ſerve turne, ſo he hid himſelfe in a Furs-Buſh.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>With my true love, I reſt: Your affectionate Friend, <hi>Raphael Hunt.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="Parliamentary_letter">
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>22. <hi>Martii.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>It is this day Ordered, That this Letter be forthwith printed.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Hen. Elſinge, Cleric. Parl. D. Com.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
